hey welcome back I'm your favorite
dysfunctional scientist and today we're
going to talk about the potential
sentience and consciousness of the tiny
human brains you can grow in a literal
jar if you want to brain organoids are
made from stem cells essentially if you
take a stem cell you can induce it to
become flurry potent which is what we
would think about of embryonic cells
brain organoids were invented roughly a
decade ago now they're made by taking a
stem cells sometimes embryonic stem
cells or sometimes fetal brain tissue
and encouraging them to grow into a
brain while disembodied these guys have
amazing medical potential but one of the
things that people figured out about
them pretty quick is that you could use
them for computation along with the rise
of AI people have been trying to combine
them with AI and they've done a pretty
good job of it the benefit that literal
human brains have over other AI models
is that they exhibit Randomness not only
can they perform a task but they can
learn to perform it in 2022 cortical ABS
shocked the world when they claimed that
they have sentient
the most basic definition of sentience
would be the ability to react to stimuli
the ability to have an experience this
concept is often confused with
Consciousness Consciousness is the
perception of self and it's a really
difficult thing to get a hold of
essentially if you want to be considered
conscious you have to understand that
you are separate from others this is why
the test that they've used for decades
has been whether or not you can
recognize yourself in a mirror turns out
even fish can do that yes fish are
self-aware and I'm kind of upset about
it I thought fish were the only thing I
could eat without feeling guilty but
apparently nah what cortical Labs did is
they taught them to play Pong if you
grow brain organoids in isolation they
tend to atrophy for not just the hypoxia
issue because they do not have a
circulatory system unless you give them
one or put it inside the skull of
another animal so they have one but they
also need something to do something to
learn just like your brain imagine
your Consciousness just being dumped
into a tub tub is dark has no stimuli
it's not really going to do very well
what they demonstrated by having these
guys play Pong is that they're better
than AI at learning to play it and they
get better at it this of course was
rather shocking and had ethicists
concerned the fact that they're able to
make decisions learn take in stimuli and
then use it to perform new tasks does
demonstrate a degree of sentience as far
as the concept of self they essentially
dropped them in the literal Matrix if
they were to have a thought about it all
they would know is pong that is her
entire world now a Swiss company final
spark took this to a whole new level
they demonstrated that you could not
just embody a disembodied brain in game
world but you could embody it with more
complex methods like our friend the
butterfly that is a butterfly being run
by human brain computers this
demonstrated that the little brains were
capable of understanding a 3D World and
they're also capable of working together
they have 16 brain organoids to a chip
and they work together and learn
together the longest they've been able
to be kept alive was about 10 months and
that just works by cycling oxygen and
nutrient Rich liquid around the brain
organoid it's essentially just diffusion
which really is not all that different
than how you get nutrients to your brain
you just have a circulatory system that
helps out with it you could use the tiny
human brains to do computation if you
wanted to for about $500 a month you can
also hop over to their website and watch
them think in real time which I will
admit is a bit disturbing final spark
did launch an international campaign
with a bunch of different research
groups to focus on different aspects of
the utilization of the tiny brains I
have chatted with them a bit about it
and I have kept asking them if they have
assigned these guys to an llm yet
because I really want to talk to a brain
organoid I've never gotten a yes or no
they just kind of skirt the question and
the answer I am continuing to keep up
with all of those research groups that
are utilizing them and as those papers
come out I will continue to let you know
here I will also post all papers that I
can in the description of every video so
you don't have to believe me you can
read it there have been some pretty
interesting papers coming out utilizing
them with AI they're very adapted
understanding human speech they can even
differentiate between one researcher and
another based on voice which is
something that an AI can do that is true
but as of currently brain organoids
learn faster which is not particularly
surprising I've always been a proponent
of biosimilar Technology Evolution has
had millions of years in fact
potentially for billion years to get
where we are today why should we try to
reinvent the wheel why don't we just use
the wheel which brings us to the
concerns of ethicists now I have had the
luck of chatting with a lot of these
research GR groups and early on when
they were claiming sentients it was
really exciting they were totally
leaning into the spooky aspects but then
everyone else started to think about it
we have had groups putting them in
charge of robots I love the freaking
spider robot okay we don't know how much
Consciousness these guys could actually
have we know that they match the
electrical signals from a baby brain
quite well some have said that they
can't technically be conscious not in
the medical terminology because they
don't have a sleep wake cycle they lack
a brain stem a brain stem is necessary
for there to be a difference between
awake and asleep but there has been
effort to give them a brain stem we also
do know that if you take just human
neurons and grow up a mouse with human
neurons in them they are smarter when we
put them inside of the brains of rodents
we know that the human architecture is
different we don't know exactly what
that looks like from the perspective of
being that Mouse I've even read these
guys being referred to as subhuman in
terms of the ethics of biotechnology and
that also feels a little bit weird
scientists have been trying to outline
where the limits are because this is
such a new technology there's not really
a place where we can say where
Consciousness has been reached and
unfortunately if we ever reached
Consciousness we would have a very hard
time identifying or accepting that we
actually created Consciousness so there
could be suffering occurring within our
tiny brain friends that we wouldn't even
be able to
perceive ultimately we don't really have
a good answer for it it will be
interesting to see what research comes
out in the next 10 years because things
are moving very quickly right now
Areo than the tiny proar swarming in the
culture